Guide to the William P. Hobby, Jr. and Diana Poteat Hobby Family Collection, ca. 1950s-2000s MS 628
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
William P. Hobby Jr. & Diana Poteat Hobby Family Collection
ca. 1950s-2000s
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Hobby, William Pettus, Jr. "Bill"
MS 628
2.75 Linear Feet
The collection includes Diana P. Hobby's writing and research notes, from the early 1950s to 2014, focused on her study of William Butler Yeats. The bulk of the collection consists of family photographs and slides from the Hobby family's worldwide travels and their frequent visits to Ireland, and to Diana Hobby's family farm in North Carolina, Forest Home, along with their equestiran endeavors and competitions, and their lives and friends in Houston, TX.
Biographical / Historical
Diana Poteat Stallings Hobby (1931-2014), the daughter of writer Laurence T. Stallings and his wife, Helen Poteat, was born in New York City. She graduated from Radcliffe College in 1952 and received her Ph.D. at Rice University in 1981. She was book editor of the Houston Post, a longtime editor of Studies in English Literature at Rice, and a lifelong champion of the humanities, libraries, and nature conservancy.
Biographical / Historical
William Pettus Hobby, Jr. (1931- ), born in Houston and a 1953 Rice University graduate, was lieutenant governor of Texas, 1973-1991. He is the namesake son of a former Texas governor and of Oveta Culp Hobby, director of the Women's Army Corps and first secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare. William P. Hobby, Sr., and his wife were publishers of the Houston Post, of which their son was president, 1963-1983. He was chancellor of the University of Houston system, 1995-1997, and taught at the University of Texas at at Rice. Married in 1954, the Hobbys had four children: Laura Hobby Beckworth, Paul W. Hobby, Andrew P. Hobby, and Katherine Hobby Gibson.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes Diana P. Hobby's writing and research notes, from the early 1950s to 2014, focused on her study of William Butler Yeats. The bulk of the collection consists of family photographs and slides from the Hobby family's worldwide travels and their frequent visits to Ireland, and to Diana Hobby's family farm in North Carolina, Forest Home, along with their equestiran endeavors and competitions, and their lives and friends in Houston, TX.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series: Papers of Diana P. Hobby and William P. Hobby, Jr.; Photographs of family at Forest Home, Caswell County, NC; Photographs, oversize; Photographs, family, friends and vacations; Slides.
Index Terms
Subjects
Literature; Social life and customs
Document Types
photographs; slides (photographs); letters (correspondence); notes
- Series I: Papers of Diana P. Hobby and William P. Hobby, Jr.
  - Typescript, senior thesis of D.P. Hobby, Radcliffe College, "The Praise of Life: A Study of the Dramatic Work of William Butler Yeats as it is Represented by Four Plays", 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Class papers, Radcliffe College, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - James P. O'Reilly to Brinsley Macnamara [John Weldon] letters, transcriptions, including transcriptions of Yeats materials, 1919-1922, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Yates 1921 correspondence, transcriptions (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hobby's precis of 1921 Yeats letters, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Yeats 1922 correspondence, transcriptions, with notes by Hobby (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hobby correspondence about Yeats and Edmund Dulac letters, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Typescript of Hobby dissertation on Yeats and Dulac (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hobby citations about Lady Augusta Gregory (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hobby notes on Yeats papers at Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hobby draft on Yeats in 1887-1888 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hobby notes on Yeats from vaious published sources (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Undated notes on Yeats (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - D.P. Hobby, "William Butler Yeats and Edmund Dulac: A Correspondence, 1916-1938, " Ph.D. dissertation (bound), Rice University, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Publicity about various publications on Yeats (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Harry Ransom Center Advisory Council minutes and correspondence, including Henri Pierre Roche exhibition proposal, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hobby correspondence, 1995-2014 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Unattributed lecture on Yeats, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - William W. Lowe to William P. Hobby, with vacation photos, 1980-04-09 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Inauguration program, State of Texas, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series II: Photographs of family at Forest Home, Caswell County, NC
  - 1950s (Box 3, Envelope 1)
  - 1962-1968, undated (Box 3, Envelope 2)
  - 1970-1977, undated (Box 3, Envelope 3)
  - 1980s (Box 3, Envelope 4)
  - 1990s (Box 3, Envelope 5-6)
  - 1992 (Box 3, Envelope 7)
  - 1995 (Box 3, Envelope 8)
  - 1996 (Box 3, Envelope 9)
  - Poteat Scholars' visit, 1998 (Box 3, Envelope 10)
  - 2000s (Box 3, Envelope 11-12)
  - William Louis Poteat historical marker (Box 3, Envelope 13)
- Series III: Photographs: oversize
  - Portraits of African-Americans, most from NC (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - W.P. Hobby in India with Prime Minister Nehru and US Pres. Eisenhower, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Andrew F. Muir (1959), Hobby children (1970), Ann & Charles Duncah, Nancy & George Rupp, Peggy Barnett, D.P. & W. P. Hobby in NM (Sept.1992) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - D.P. & W.P. Hobby, Jessica Catto, Hobby children, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - D.P. & W.P. Hobby, fox hunt, Ireland, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Photographs: family, friends, vacations
  - 1950s and earlier (Box 4, Envelope 6)
  - 1960s (Box 4, Envelope 7-10)
  - 1960s; includes Lady Bird Johnson (Box 4, Envelope 11)
  - 1970s (Box 4, Envelope 12)
  - 1960s-1980s (Box 4, Envelope 13)
  - 1990s; includes Robert F. Patten (Box 4, Envelope 14)
  - 1990s; includes Marguerite Johnston Barnes (Box 4, Envelope 15)
  - 2000s (Box 4, Envelope 16)
  - 1960s-1973 (Box 4, Envelope 17)
  - Hobby's North Blvd. house with horses and carriages, 1993 (Box 4, Envelope 18)
  - D.P. & W.P. Hobby (Box 4, Envelope 19)
  - Friends, including Caitlin Finn, Duncan Shumate, Glenn Burt, Gertrude Barnstone, Marguerite Johnston Barnes, 1950s-2000 (Box 4, Envelope 20)
  - Vacations
    - Skiing: Colorado, Montana, 1974-1989 (Box 5, Envelope 1)
    - Scotland, including Paul Hobby, Louie Welch, Bob Eckels, 1977 (Box 5, Envelope 2)
    - Ireland, 1970s (Box 5, Envelope 3)
    - August 1974 (Box 5, Envelope 4)
    - Big Bend, TX, 1977 (Box 5, Envelope 5)
    - Ireland; includes Renee & Frank E. Vandiver, 1978-1992 (Box 5, Envelope 6)
    - Colorado, Montana, Syria, Spain, including Kay Bailey & Ray Hutchison, 1991-1994 (Box 5, Envelope 7)
    - Alaska, Colorado, Canada, 1985-1988 (Box 5, Envelope 8)
    - New Mexico, including Anne & Charles Duncan, Nancy & George Rupp, Peggy & Bill Barnett, 1992 (Box 5, Envelope 9)
    - China, 1994 (Box 5, Envelope 10)
    - Cuernavaca, Mexico & Spain, 1997 (Box 5, Envelope 11)
    - Estonia, Mexico, Montana, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Envelope 12)
    - Montana, [Corpus Christi, TX?], 1999 (Box 5, Envelope 13)
    - U.K., Friends of Fondren [Rice Univ.] library tour, 2000 (Box 5, Envelope 14)
    - Quebec, various locations, [Colorado/Montana?], 2000-2007 (Box 5, Envelope 15)
    - Mexico, undated (Box 5, Envelope 16)
    - Africa, Egypt, Israel, Turkey, undated (Box 5, Envelope 17)
    - Ireland, Scotland, undated (Box 5, Envelope 18)
    - various locations, undated (Box 5, Envelope 19)
    - various locations; including Mark White, undated (Box 5, Envelope 20)
- Series V: Slides
  - Hobby family; including LBJ, 1954-1982, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Family, 1960s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Family, West Texas & Ireland, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - W.P. & D.P. Hobby campaigning; Hobby family, 1970s-1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Family vacation, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - China [see box 5, folder 8], 1994 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Hobby family at Forest Home; including LBJ, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - D.P. & W.P. Hobby, Rice campus, Studies in English Literature office in Fondren Library, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Foreign travel, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)